Guide to the Ezra Laderman Papers
Yale University Music Library
- Music
  - Oratorios and Cantatas, 1960-2013
    - Voices, 2013 (Box 38, Box 38A)
      Contains two versions. One for small chamber orchestra and vocal group and the other for string quartet, soprano, tenor, and baritone.
      Text by Robert Pinsky, based on Dante's "Inferno."
  - Film and TV Scores, 1960-1973
    - Bible As Literature, 1971 (Box 35)
      Short score to film "Bible as Literature" by John Barnes.
    - Black Fox, 1963 (Box 35)
    - Burden of the Mystery, 1970 (Box 35)
      Short score to the film "Burden of the Mystery" by John Keato.
    - California the Most, 1969 (Box 35)
      Short score for the NBC special.
    - Cave People of the Philippines, 1972 (Box 37, Folder 3)
      Score for the 1972 NBC special.
    - Cycle of Death, no date (Box 37, Folder 4)
      Score to film "Cycle of Death".
    - Eleanor Roosevelt Story, 1968 (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Ellery Queen, 1969 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Endangered Species, 1960 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Forgotten Peninsula, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - Grand Canyon, 1965 (Box 39, Folder 2)
      Score from the NBC special with Joseph Wood Krutch.
    - Greek Myths, no date (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - I See a Village, 1968 (Box 39, Folder 3A)
      Includes notes and a script for the film, "I See a Village" (no music). Directed by Richard Kaplan.
    - Image of Love, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 4, Box 29A)
    - The Invisible City, no date (Box 39, Folder 5)
    - The Lincoln Mask, no date (Box 38)
    - A Mass for Cain, 1973 (Box 38, Box 39, Folder 6-8, Box 40)
      Includes "Lament Before Mass" and "Beginning, Isaiah".
    - The Meaning of Art, 1967 (Box 38)
    - My Year in the Desert, no date (Box 41, Folder 1)
      Score to NBC TV special "My Year in the Desert" by Joseph Wood Krutch.
    - NBC Movie Parts, 1959 (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Pace, 1968 (Box 40, Box 41, Folder 3)
      Pace recorded as a theme for CBS TV special "Lamp Unto My Feet". Recorded by Bamburgh Symphony. Sketches and scores to "Lamp Unto My Feet" and "Thema and Intermezzi" also included.
    - Voice of the Desert, no date (Box 41, Folder 4, Box 40)
  - Dedications (Box 78)
    Photocopies of melodies written for friends.
  - Unfinished pieces (Box 43)
    Material in this subseries includes works described by Laderman as "uncompleted", or "abandoned". Two of the pieces are labeled "false starts". Also included are unfinished orchestral versions of other (complete) pieces.
  - Sketches (Box 46–48)
    Most of the sketches are not identified. The majority are pencil sketches, although there are some photocopies. Also included are sketch notebooks.
  - Potential libretti (Box 46A)
    These libretti were given to Ezra Laderman for consideration.
  - Unidentified pieces (Box 45)
  - Unidentified fragments (Box 44)
    Contains unidentified portions of various works.
  - Untitled fragments of scripts and libretti (Box 78)
- Audiovisual
  - Reel-to-reel audio tapes
    The reel-to-reel tapes are listed by box. Titles are transcribed directly from the cases.
    - Violin concerto (Box 49)
    - Galileo - 1 (Box 49)
    - Galileo - 2 (Box 49)
    - Galileo - 3 (Box 49)
    - Violin Concerto (Box 49)
    - Celestial Bodies (Hoover) (Box 49)
    - Invisible City (Box 49)
    - E.L. Interview on WQXR (Box 49)
    - Elegy (Box 49)
    - The Black Fox Reel #11 (Box 49)
    - Laderman From The Psalms (Box 49)
    - Galileo 2/10/79 - Directional Mikes (Box 49)
    - Laderman Galileo Pt 2 (Box 49)
    - Louisville Orchestra: Making Music on the Air: Program #53 (Box 49)
    - Grand Canyon #2 (Box 50)
    - NBC News #2 (Box 50)
    - Seminar '77 (Box 50)
    - The Endangered Species Print Takes (Box 50)
    - Invisible City 1961 (Box 50)
    - Grand Canyon (Box 50)
    - American Profile Reel 1 (Box 50)
    - American Profile Reel 2 (Box 50)
    - Worship (Box 50)
    - Bennington Composers conf. (Box 50)
    - Laderman Symphony #3 ("Jerusalem") (Box 50)
    - CMU String Quartet (Box 50)
    - Symphony No. 1 R#1 (Box 50)
    - Stanzas (Box 50)
    - Cincinaty [sic] Orch. (Box 50)
    - Laderman - Songs for Eve (Box 50)
    - Viola (Box 50)
    - Visions '75 Columbus (Box 50)
    - Scenes From An Imagined (Box 50)
    - Viola Concerto (Eastman) (Box 50)
    - Pre-Hispanic (CBS TV) (Box 50)
    - Violin Concerto (Oliveira, Phil.) (Box 50)
    - Jacob + The Indians (Box 50)
    - Five Trios + Fantasy (Box 50)
    - Laderman #5 4/15/78 (Concord) (Box 50)
    - Symphony No 2 Bamberg (Box 50)
    - Bassoon Concerto (Goldstein) (Box 50)
    - Nonette (Box 50)
    - Rehearsal for Harlequande (Box 50)
    - Laderman: Stanzas for Chamber Orchestra (Box 50)
    - Laderman - C. Bodies - 6/23/75 (Box 50)
    - Brass Quintet/Prelude for Orch. (Box 50)
    - Piano Sonata 1/Them + Variations Vln + Pno (Box 51)
    - Esther (Rehearsal) CBS/TV (Box 51)
    - Elegy (Box 51)
    - "Ulysses" Music (Box 51)
    - "Ulysses" Music (Box 51)
    - Oboe Quartet (Box 51)
    - Interview 1973 (Box 51)
    - Chamber Concerto (Rehearsal) Dance (Box 51)
    - Evansville Chamber Players (Box 51)
    - Dominique #3 (Box 51)
    - Double Helix '68 (Box 51)
    - Quartet No 7 (Col.) (Box 51)
    - Violin/Cello Duo (Box 51)
    - Celestial Bodies (Box 51)
    - Fantasy for W.W. Quintet '75 (Box 51)
    - Duo for Violin + Piano (Box 51)
    - Cello Partita (Box 51)
    - String Quartet #2 (Box 51)
    - Esther Laderman (Box 51)
    - Hunting of Snark (Box 51)
    - Laderman: Five Portraits (Box 51)
    - Laderman: Violin Sonata (Box 51)
    - E.R. Story #1 (Box 51)
    - E.R. Story #2 (Box 51)
    - Califonia I (Box 51)
    - Echoes in Anticipation (Box 51)
    - A Handful of Souls I (Box 51)
    - A Handful of Souls II (Box 51)
    - Snark (Box 51)
    - Nonette (Box 52)
    - Double Helix (Box 52)
    - Laderman: St Qt No. 2 (Box 52)
    - String Quartet #2 (Box 51)
    - String Quartet No#2 (Box 52)
    - Magic Prison Mono (Box 52)
    - Nonette (Box 52)
    - Laderman - St 4tet #2 World Premiere (Box 52)
    - Magic Prison Soundtrack (Box 52)
    - Laderman: Violin Sonata (Box 52)
    - Duo for Violin + Piano (premier) (Box 52)
    - String Quartet #2 (Box 52)
    - String Quartet #2 (Box 52)
    - Image of Love #3 (Box 52)
    - Laderman/Darion: Galileo - reel 1 (Box 52)
    - Laderman/Darion: Galileo - reel 2 (Box 52)
    - Laderman/Darion: Galileo - reel 3 (Box 52)
    - Lamp Unto My Feet (Box 52)
    - String Quartet #1 (Box 52)
    - Nonette (Box 52)
    - Kaleidoscope: Three Cities in the Nuclear Age Reel #2 of 2 (Box 52)
    - Luther (Box 52)
    - Laderman: Songs for Eve (Box 52)
    - Laderman - Songs for Eve (Box 52)
    - Snark 1-4 (Box 53)
    - A Single Voice Oboe (Box 53)
    - Lib. of Congress '71 "Scenes From..." (Box 53)
    - Pace '70 (Box 53)
    - And David Wept - I (Box 53)
    - And David Wept II (Box 53)
    - The Ensemble Caspary Auditorium Wednesday 17 November 1976 at 8:00 p.m. (Box 53)
    - Dominique I - Part 1 (Box 53)
    - Laderman: A Single Voice (Spoleto '67) (Box 53)
    - Cavemen of the Phillipenes [sic] (NBC TV) (Box 53)
    - Laderman: "Symphony No. 1" (Box 53)
    - Snark 1-4 (Piano) (Box 53)
    - Piano Sonata No. 1 (Ponce) (Box 53)
    - Elegy For Viola (Box 53)
    - Laderman Elegy For viola (Box 53)
    - Other Voices for Viola (1 Track) (Box 53)
    - Other Voices/Viola (Box 53)
    - Songs by E.L. (Snark 5-8) (Box 53)
    - Laderman - Symph I (Box 53)
    - Violin Concerto (Box 53)
    - Duo Violin + Cello (Box 53)
    - In The Fall Of 1844 (Box 53)
    - Duo Violin - Cello (Box 53)
    - Black Fox (Box 53)
    - Quartet No 3 (Box 53)
    - 5/84 Library of Congress, Wash D.C. Quartet No 7. (Box 53)
    - Quartet No 4 (Box 53)
    - Evansville Chamber Players (Box 53)
    - Duo for Violin + Cello (Box 53)
    - Dominique (Box 53)
    - South Pacific Snark 5-8 (Box 53)
    - Double Helix, Cadence (Box 54)
    - Celestial Bodies (Box 54)
    - Quartet No. 7 Colorado (Box 54)
    - Quartet No#3 (Lenox) (Box 54)
    - Laderman String Quartet #4 (Box 54)
    - Quartet No. 5 (Concord) (Box 54)
    - Meaning of Art #2 (Box 54)
    - "Image of Love" Reel #1 (Box 54)
    - "Image of Love" Reel #2 (Box 54)
    - Meaning of Art R1 (Box 54)
    - 201 # 17-A Interview '67 (Box 54)
    - Laderman Galileo Pt 2. (Box 54)
    - Galileo 2/10/79 Omni Directional Mixer (Box 54)
    - Concerto For Orch./Baltimore (Box 54)
    - Convocation E.L. '70 (Box 54)
    - Octet (Box 54)
    - A Festival of Ladermusic '78 (Box 54)
    - A Festival of Ladermusic ' 78 (Box 54)
    - Stanzas I-V (Box 54)
    - Leipzig '45/PNO CON. '39/Preludes (Box 54)
    - NBC TV News II (Box 54)
    - Bennington '67/'68 (Box 54)
    - Magic Prison (NY Phil.) (Box 54)
    - A Handful of Souls (Air) (Box 79)
    - 2 Track Stereo N.A. 15 ips. Tails Out (Box 79)
    - Chicago Symphony Orchestra (Box 79)
    - Ezra Laderman American Profile (Box 79)
    - TDK (Box 79)
    - Capitol Chamber Artists (Box 79)
    - [Unmarked 10 inch reel] (Box 80)
    - [Unmarked 5 inch reel] (Box 80)
  - Film reels, VHS and DVD
    - Tribute to Ezra Laderman at Binghamton, 3/5/04; VHS tape and DVD. (Box 80)
    - The Eagle Stirred, 4/9/1961 (Box 83)
      Part one.
    - The Eagle Stirred, 4/9/1961 (Box 84)
      Part 2.
    - Look Up and Live (Box 85)
    - Look Up and Live (Box 86)
    - Laderman Magic Prison Color NY Philharmonic (Box 87)
    - Laderman Keats (A Film) (Box 88)
    - Leonardo Da Vinci (Box 89)
    - The Renaissance (Box 90)
    - The Oregon Trail (Box 91)
    - The Renaissance (Box 92)
- Correspondence, 1929-2015
  This series contains correspondence sent and received by Ezra Laderman. The series is divided into three subseries: 1. Correspondence with significant individuals; 2. Correspondence by subject - which includes organizations, specific individuals, and correspondence concerning specific pieces Laderman composed; and 3. Correspondence by date.
  - Correspondence with significant individuals
    - A-Q (Box 55)
    - R-Z (Box 56, Folder 1, 2, and 3)
  - Correspondence by subject
    - American Composers Alliance (Box 56, Folder 4)
    - American Composer's Orchestra (Box 56, Folder 5)
    - American Music Center (Box 56, Folder 6)
    - ASCAP (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - CBS TV (Box 56, Folder 8)
    - Contracts (Box 56, Folder 9)
    - Copyists + (Blue Printing) (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - Court Case (Box 57, Folder 2)
    - EBC (Box 57, Folder 3)
    - "Get Well" Correspondence (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - Marilyn (Box 57, Folder 5)
    - NEA (Box 57, Folder 6)
    - National Music Council (Box 57, Folder 7)
    - New York Times (Box 57, Folder 8)
    - Oxford University Press (Box 57, Folder 9)
    - Rejection Letters (Box 57, Folder 10)
    - Rockefeller FDN (Minneapolis Symphony) (Box 57, Folder 11)
    - SUNY (Box 57, Folder 12)
    - Student "Thank You" Correspondence (Box 57, Folder 13)
    - And David Wept (Box 58, Folder 1)
    - Magic Prison/ Songs For Eve (Box 58, Folder 2)
    - Violin Concerto, Organ Preludes, Piano Trio (Box 58, Folder 3)
    - String Quartets Nos. 1-3 (Box 58, Folder 4)
    - Theme, Variations, and Finale/Stanzas (Box 58, Folder 5)
    - Violin, Flute, and Clarinet Sonatas (Box 58, Folder 6)
    - A Single Voice and Various Shorter Works (Box 58, Folder 7)
    - Galileo (Box 59, Folder 1 and 2)
    - Double Helix/Celestial Bodies (Box 59, Folder 3)
    - Momente, From The Psalms, 5 Trios and a Fanfare, Duo for Violin and Piano (Box 59, Folder 4)
    - Satine, Duo for Flute and Dancer (Box 59, Folder 5)
    - Piano Sonatas 1 and 2, Portraits (Box 59, Folder 6)
    - Octet, Nonette (Box 59, Folder 7)
    - Songs From Michelangelo (Box 59, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence by date
    - 1920's - 1979 (Box 60)
    - 1980 - 1989 (Box 61)
    - 1990 - 2015, Undated (Box 62)
- Writings, professional activities and photographs
  - Writings, 1940-1999 (Box 68)
    Includes newspaper articles, music reviews, school assigments, speeches, interviews, scripts, and autobiographical material.
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters material (Box 68)
    Includes newspaper articles, correspondence, membership information, and Laderman's presidential address.
  - NEA-related material
    Material from Laderman's time as a member of the National Endowment for the Arts. Includes NEA guidelines, meeting agendas, grant proposals (both approved and rejected), correspondence, and other financial information.
    - 1973 - 1975 (Box 69)
    - 1975 - 1976 (Box 70)
    - 1976 - 1977 (Box 71)
    - 1977 - 1978 (Box 72)
    - 1979 - 1981 (Box 73)
    - 1981, General Plan for 1980 - 1984 (Box 74)
      Also includes composer librettist translator program grant applications, 1975.
  - Competitions and awards (Box 81)
    Includes material related to various institutions for whom Laderman acted as judge for music competitions.
  - Contracts (Box 81)
  - Biographical notes (Box 81)
  - Yale-related material (Box 82)
    Materials related to Laderman's professorship at the Yale School of Music, including programs, documents, course materials, and brochures from Yale alumni tours which Laderman attended as a professor.
  - Photographs (Box 93)
    Photographs consist of professional headshots, Laderman composing and conducting, and Laderman with colleagues and students. Also included are photos from ASCAP and the American Academy of Arts and Letters.
  - Notes from performances and recordings (Box 82)
  - Drafts of letters, miscellaneous notes, addresses and invitations (Box 82, Box 94)
- Clippings and publicity, 1941-2016
  Series consists of loose newspaper and magazine clippings related to Laderman's music. Also included are two albums, one containing clippings related to "Marilyn", and the other from the 1960s. Note that posters for The Hunting of the Snark and The Eleanor Roosevelt Story are housed in Box 93.
  Clippings are arranged chronologically.
  - 1940's - 1990's (Box 76)
  - 1990's - 2016, undated (Box 77)
- Programs and related materials, 1940-2015
  The bulk of this series consists of programs from performances of Laderman's music. Also included are handwritten and typewritten program notes, most of which were written by Laderman himself. The final two subseries contain programs from concerts which do not include Laderman's music (presumably concerts Laderman attended), and programs for non-music events such as graduation ceremonies and dinners.
  - Laderman programs by date
    - 1940 - 1978 (Box 63)
    - 1979 - 1985 (Box 64)
    - 1986 - 1993 (Box 65)
    - 1994 - 2003 (Box 66)
    - 2004 - 2015, undated programs (Box 67)
  - Program notes (Box 75)
    Includes program notes for various pieces, most of which written by Laderman himself.
  - Press releases for concerts (Box 75)
    Press release information regarding important performances of Laderman's music.
  - Non-Laderman concerts (Box 75)
    Includes various programs which do not include Laderman music.
  - Other program materials (Box 75)
    Includes commencement and ceremonial event programs, schedules for lectures given by Laderman, and music magazines.
- Documents and awards
  - Passports, ASCAP membership certificate and union membership cards (Box 94)
  - Degrees and school report cards (Box 94)
  - Parents' Association Award for Excellence in Theory and Composition (High School of Music and Art, 1941) (Box 94)
  - The National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences Award for Outstanding Achievement in Cultural Documentaries: Galileo (1967-68) (Box 94)
  - Brooklyn College Distinguished Alumnus Award (1984) (Box 94)
  - National Guild of Community Schools of the Arts New York Metropolitan Chapter, Distinguished Alumnus Award For Outstanding Services to the Arts (1986) (Box 95)
  - In Recognition of Outstanding Contributions to American Orchestras as a member of The American Symphony Orchestra League Board of Directors 1987-1992 (Box 96)